Let's dive into our app.
One of the questions that might be coming up is,
you might be thinking, well, okay, in view three,
there are two ways of authoring components.
There's the options API and the composition API,
which we'll be using today.
I will be showing you both because both
are still valid ways of writing components in view,
but we will definitely be spending more time
in composition API for I'll explain later why.
But this way, if people get a flavor of how it feels
to be in both in that way, you don't feel
like you have to do one of the other when it comes
to building your own project.
So let's start with a scenario that we're all
pretty familiar with when it comes to view.
Let's go ahead and take a look at the Nav bar component.
Okay, so this Nav bar component,
let's contextualize what's going on here.
So let me go ahead and open up here.
The Nav bar is this piece up top.
And so typically in the Nav bar,
we might have, like, say, a tagline as a problem
that we'd passed down.
So if we look at app.view here, we have the Nav bar,
and we want to define what it might be, right?
So typically, I might be like, okay,
well, my tagline here is track everything you want to eat.
This is great.
And so if we switch back over to the site,
you'll see it appears up here in the upper left.
Everything seems pretty good.
But for anyone who's worked with code for a while,
you'll notice that one of the problems here
with the way we've defined the props is that it doesn't
tell you very much besides what it's called.
And so what we want to do, even prior to TypeScript,
is we'd want to actually define more information
about the props.
So the way we would do this typically in standard view,
is you would say, okay, we'd make props
in object instead of an array.
And then the tagline here, we can actually define what type it is.
So we might be like, it's a string, for example.
This is what we expect.
And so typically, you'll even dive a little bit further
by actually having it say, okay, type string.
And then you can have it to have either default property
or the required property.
So in this case, we'll go ahead and just do that real quick.
So this is feeling a lot better, right?
This is what most of us are familiar with.
And if we wanted to do, like, and so this was nice
because what we would get to do is we'd say, okay, now
we can do things like, okay, in our data property,
we can say, okay, we have a tagline.
And this is, let's just say, test string for now.
And we can now make this a reactive property,
and this is great.
And so we can see here, everything still works.
But the problem was, what happened when someone passed
the wrong thing?
And so this is where it was nice, because in the case
someone passed, like, one, two, three, for example,
and this is a number, what we find is that inside of our app,
when we actually open it up, you'll see that there's an invalid
prop type check, which is nice because something is yelling
at us.
On the other hand, if you don't have your console open
and you're not paying attention for this, if you look back
in our code, there's really nothing to indicate
that anything else is wrong.
And so this is a limitation on prop type checking.
But if we really think about it, though,
this is actually the kind of mental model
that TypeScript is really built around anyways,
which is around documenting what you intend to do,
and then helping you to just sort of prevent yourself
from making mistakes in that regard.
So in this case, in the event, we really wanted
to be a string or a number.
We could just say, oh, okay, well, it's a string or a number.
Like, this was like a default syntax
that's built right out of the box for view,
which was really nice.
And so here's another limitation that you probably have run
into when it comes to the prop type checking
that we have with you.
So let's go and take a look at restaurant card, for example.
I don't know about you, how many people have done this before
where you have an object that you're passing down
to a component and the type is just object.
Now, that's nice from at least knowing what the primitive is,
but then otherwise you have no idea what's inside of that
shape, and then oftentimes you find yourself switching
between files, you might miss some things.
It'd be nice if this was a little bit better.
So first thing first here, we have this restaurant.
And let's see, again, how will we typically debug this?
We would say, okay, well, the restaurant is being
where's that being passed?
Well, let's take a look.
So if I go inside of here, and I look for restaurant card,
restaurant card I, it's being imported on restaurant page.
All right, restaurant page here is, let's see the scroll,
the way down, and you're like, oh, okay, here is where
it's being called, and it's being passed by the item.
The item is passed by filter lists.
So if I then go ahead and hold option click on this,
it would jump me up to where filter restaurant lists is,
and then I, yes, here are the restaurants that I can jump up.
And, okay, here's the shape of my data, right?
This is kind of how the process is.
This is actually pretty normal for us to debug.
But this is a lot of work, especially when code bases
can get infinitely more complex.
Now, because some of you might have been like, oh, well,
I would have guessed it was that, but we all know, right?
code does not always organize as well.
So that's usually how you might debug it.
So we might be like, okay, okay, so we know this is the thing.
So let's copy it over, let's go into restaurant card.
And let's at least document it somewhere, right?
So we might be like, let's just create like a comment block
and just be like, okay, restaurant, so what do we got?
We got like ID, so the ID is typically like a string,
and then we have, in fact, these are all strings.
So let's just, at the bare minimum, let's document the shape.
So let me just multiply, cursor select.
So for those of you that haven't done this before,
I'm just holding down a command, while clicking,
I think it might be control on Windows.
And so this is the general shape that we have for our restaurant.
And so once we have this, normally you would throw this
in like a JS doc block, and then you know,
you would hopefully be able to pick some of that up,
and that would be nice.
But we're here to learn about TypeScript
and how that looks, right?
So now that we have this shape, let me just go ahead
and actually comment this as so it doesn't report any errors.
And let's go ahead and actually make sure
that we tell you that we want to use TypeScript
for this specific component.
And so the way we do this is we come up here inside the script block
and we declare its language.
And so language equals TS which stands for TypeScript.
That's it.
Once you've done that, you've basically told you
time to use the TypeScript compiler.
And then the next thing we need to do though
is that we need to actually tell TypeScript
what kind of object we're about to pass into it,
because what you'll notice here is that inside of you,
one of the things that sets it apart from the framers
is that it does this export default object thing.
And that has sometimes mixed result,
especially when it comes to types.
So what we have is this helper function
called define component from view.
So when you import this, it basically tells TypeScript
what to expect and kind of roughly what to guess
when it's making a bunch of assumptions about your component.
And so then instead of just exporting a default generic object,
now we're going to say we're going to wrap it
in define component, whoops, and then we wrap that
on the bottom, and then that's it.
So far so good.
Of course, now the question is, OK, how do we
tell it that we wanted to actually become this restaurant type?
And so for now, what we're going to do
is we're going to learn about how to declare types.
And so we actually can do it directly inside this component.
We're not going to get crazy here.
We're going to create a custom type called restaurant.
And so this keyword here, if you've never used TypeScript before,
is specific to TypeScript.
Basically, it's a constant let.
What are you declaring?
Do you're declaring a type?
We're declaring a type of restaurant.
And the shape of this object is going to be this thing
that I just created.
So I'm going to kind of paste this over here and show it like this.
And so what you'll notice here is that there's
a couple of syntactical things that might look a little bit odd,
like there's no commas or anything.
But this is just how it is defined.
And for those who have a little bit of TypeScript knowledge,
you might be wondering, well, what about interfaces
and yada, for the purposes of keeping things
approachable and simple, we're sticking with types for now.
It's one of the things where as you need interface
in that kind of stuff, we'll reach out for it.
But for now, we're just going to keep it simple with types.
OK, now that we have this, you're probably
thinking, OK, I know what I'm going to do.
I'm going to come in here and I'm going to say a restaurant.
And everything is going to be fixed.
Except wait a second, what's going on here?
Oh, it says that it's only referring to a type,
but it's being used as a value here.
And so this is where it's a little bit weird, right?
Because this is not what you would typically expect.
But what we have here, and this is where
you're going to need to learn a new thing when you're using
options API, is that one of the things we have to do
in, when using TypeScript with it, is using this as keyword.
And this is known as typecasting, where
basically telling typeScript explicitly what it's going to be.
And because we're using options API, again,
this is some of the hacks around that makes it
a little bit trickier compared to composition API,
is that we need something called a prop type.
So what I'm going to do is import a type called prop type from view.
And so this is one of those things that we need,
in order, once again, to help TypeScript understand
the convention that optioned API provides for developers.
And so what we do is we say, well, we need the object
to be a prop type.
And then we have this new convention in TypeScript,
which is the bracket, greater than less than simple.
And if you think of them like parentheses,
like you're passing in an argument, think of it like that.
Like you're saying, oh, I have a prop type that's
going to be a type restaurant.
But because this is TypeScript, it wants to be explicit,
then it is important, not even important.
It has to be the greater and less than symbols.
And just like that now, you'll see that if we hover over a restaurant,
it'll actually let you know it's a prop type restaurant.
And now going forward, you can actually learn more
about the thing that you're working with
before having to jump around different files.
And this is super nice.